<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/site/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/site/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-08-24T01:56:32+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/site/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Ari Fischer</title><subtitle>Researching chemistry-based solutions to the problems surrounding energy and sustainable materials production that define our times!</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Steady-state kinetics with kinetic Monte Carlo in Python and the connection to mean field kinetic descriptions.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/site/kinetics/tutorials/2023/08/19/kMC_tutorial_2_steadystate.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Steady-state kinetics with kinetic Monte Carlo in Python and the connection to mean field kinetic descriptions." /><published>2023-08-19T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2023-08-19T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/site/kinetics/tutorials/2023/08/19/kMC_tutorial_2_steadystate</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/site/kinetics/tutorials/2023/08/19/kMC_tutorial_2_steadystate.html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/site/assets/images/KMC_tutorial_2/TOC.png" alt="TOC" /></p>

<p><em>Introduction:</em></p>

<p>The previous guide
(<a href="https://ari-fischer.github.io/site/kinetics/tutorials/2023/07/23/KMC_tutorial_1_equilibrium.html">https://ari-fischer.github.io/site/kinetics/tutorials/2023/07/23/KMC_tutorial_1_equilibrium.html</a>)
introduced the concept of kinetic Monte Carlo (kMC) and built a code to
simulate the dynamics of reactant <em>A</em> conversion into product <em>B</em> at a
catalytic surface. The mole fraction of <em>A</em> and <em>B</em> that the catalyst
surface was exposed to was evolved from an initial state consisting of
only <em>A</em> to a final state reflecting thermodynamic equilibrium between
<em>A</em> and <em>B</em>. The true power of kMC, however, lies in determining kinetic
behaviors for complex systems, rather than determining thermodynamic
endpoints which are independent of the path taken by the system. The
reader is referred to Andersen et al. for some examples where kMC has
been applied to study the kinetics of surface diffusion, crystal growth,
and heterogeneous catalysis [1].</p>

<p>Here, a kMC model of the same <em>A</em> to <em>B</em> reaction is employed to
simulate steady-state dynamics and obtain reaction rates and effective
rate constants. These rates and parameters are shown to be identical to
those obtained by analyzing Langmuir-Hinshelwood kinetics for the same
reaction. In doing so, it becomes clear how dynamic behaviors gleaned
from kMC simulations reflect the same kinetics as those from mean-field
descriptions of reaction kinetics.</p>

<p><em>Analyzing steady-state kinetics with mean field kinetic descriptions:</em></p>

<p>Scheme 1 shows the sequence of elementary steps that mediates <em>A</em>
conversion to <em>B</em> on a catalyst surface. Step 1 shows the adsorption
of <em>A</em> to a vacant *-site (denoted by *) to form <em>A</em> to form <em>A</em>*.
Step 2 shows the conversion of <em>A</em>* to <em>B</em>* at the surface. Step 3
shows the desorption of <em>B</em>* to form the product <em>B</em> and a vacant *-site.</p>

<p><strong>Scheme 1</strong>: A sequence of elementary steps for the conversion of
species <em>A</em> to <em>B</em> on a catalytic site (denoted by *). The <em>k<sub>i</sub></em> terms
represent forward and reverse rate constants for each reaction step.</p>

<p><img src="/site/assets/images/KMC_tutorial_2/scheme1.png" alt="Scheme 1" /></p>

<p>Mean field rate expressions for each of the elementary step in Scheme 1
occurring on <em>L<sub>*</sub></em> active sites are obtained by considering each step
to be reversible and with their forward and reverse rates related to
reactant mole fractions from the law of mass action (i.e. that the rate
of reaction is proportional to the product of reactant thermodynamic
activities) [2]:</p>

<p><img src="/site/assets/images/KMC_tutorial_2/eqn1.png" alt="eq 1" /></p>

<p>Here, <em>y<sub>A</sub></em> and <em>y<sub>B</sub></em> are the mole fractions of <em>A</em> and <em>B</em>,
respectively; θ<sub>A</sub>, θ<sub>B</sub>, and θ<sub><em>&lt;/sub&gt; are the
fractional surface coverages of *A</em>, <em>B</em> and vacancies on <em>L*</em> sites;
and <em>k<sub>i</sub></em> are rate constants with corresponding steps denoted in Scheme
1.</sub></p>

<p>An analytical expression for the rate of <em>B</em> formation can be derived
based on the following assumptions consistent with the values of rate
constants in Table 1. First, <em>B</em>* desorbs much faster than it reacts at
the surface to re-form <em>A</em>* (<em>k<sub>-B</sub></em>/<em>k<sub>BA</sub></em>=100000), indicating that
<em>B</em>* formation in Step 2 is irreversible. The rate of Step 2 can
therefore be restated as:</p>

<p><img src="/site/assets/images/KMC_tutorial_2/eqn2.png" alt="eq 2" /></p>

<p>Secondly, <em>A</em>* desorbs much faster than it reacts to form <em>B</em>*
(<em>k<sub>-A</sub></em>/<em>k<sub>AB</sub></em>=100) indicating that Step 1 occurs at quasi-equilibrium
(i.e. the forward and reverse rates of Step 1 are both much larger than
the net rate of reaction). Approximating the net rate of Step 1 as zero
gives the quasi-equilibrium coverage of <em>A</em>*:</p>

<p><img src="/site/assets/images/KMC_tutorial_2/eqn3.png" alt="eq 3" /></p>

<p>The coverage of vacant *-sites, <em>A</em>*, and <em>B</em>* are related by the
conservation of occupied and unoccupied <em>L</em>* sites, given by:</p>

<p><img src="/site/assets/images/KMC_tutorial_2/eqn4.png" alt="eq 4" /></p>

<p>The coverage of <em>B</em>* is assumed to be negligible at low conversion (low
<em>y<sub>B</sub></em>) because <em>B</em>* desorbs faster than it adsorbs
(<em>k<sub>-B</sub></em>/<em>k<sub>B</sub></em>=10). An expression for θ<sub>*</sub> can be obtained by
neglecting the θ<sub>B</sub> term, replacing θ<sub>A</sub> with its value
from equation 5, and solving for θ<sub>*</sub>:</p>

<p><img src="/site/assets/images/KMC_tutorial_2/eqn5.png" alt="eq 5" /></p>

<p>The net rate of <em>B</em> formation is obtained by replacing the θ<sub>*</sub>
term in equation 5 with its value from equation 7, and then substituting
the resulting expression for θ<sub>A</sub> into equation 4:</p>

<p><img src="/site/assets/images/KMC_tutorial_2/eqn6.png" alt="eq 6" /></p>

<p>This equation thus relates the rate of <em>B</em> formation normalized by the
number of *-sites to the mole fraction of <em>A</em> and the kinetic constants
for its reaction at *-sites.</p>

<p><img src="/site/assets/images/KMC_tutorial_2/table1.png" alt="table 1" /></p>

<p>Figure 1 shows the effect of <em>y<sub>A</sub></em> on the coverages of vacant *-sites
and <em>A</em>* (left) and on the rate of <em>B</em> formation (right) (with <em>y<sub>A</sub></em>
changed by diluting <em>A</em> with an inert gas like He). Intuitively,
coverages of <em>A*</em> increase and vacant * decrease as <em>y<sub>A</sub></em> increases
and <em>A</em> adsorption becomes more favorable. The rate of <em>B</em> formation
increases proportional to the <em>A*</em> coverage, reflecting the functional
form of equation 4.</p>

<p><img src="/site/assets/images/KMC_tutorial_2/figure1.png" alt="figure 1" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 1:</strong> <em>A</em>* and vacant *-site coverages (left) and <em>B</em>
formation rate (right) as a function of <em>A</em> mole fraction (<em>y<sub>A</sub></em>).</p>

<p>Equation 8 relates the macroscopic rate of <em>B</em> formation to the
macroscopic mole fraction of reactant <em>A</em>. Its derivation requires a
fractional coverage of active sites to be defined, which implicitly
requires a large number of active sites so that fractional coverages
behave as continuous functions. This rate expression is a faithful
description of reactivity only at length and time scales in the
thermodynamic limit where these macroscopic observables are significant.
The single active site considered in the kMC model from the previous
walkthrough, on the other hand, considers only a single active site,
that is either occupied or unoccupied, but cannot partially occupied.
Moreover, products are formed one at a time by the desorption of <em>B</em>
from a <em>B</em>-covered *-site in a stochastic manner, rather than forming
continuously at a constant rate.</p>

<p>The reaction we are considering has properties that enables its
microscopic and macroscopic observables to be related. First, it is
Markovian, meaning that the next step taken from the current state
depends only on the present configuration, but not on the previous steps
[2]. It is also ergodic, meaning that all possible states of the
system are dynamically accessible from one another [2]. Finally, the
process has time-translational symmetry, meaning that the probabilities
for transitioning from one state to another depends only on relative,
but not absolute, time [2]. For systems with these properties, the
probability of finding the system in each of the possible states follows
a unique distribution after a long enough simulation time.</p>

<p>In the example catalytic reaction, for instance, the average amount of
time that the system is found in states <em>A</em>*, <em>B</em>*, or * reflects the
unique probability of finding the system in that state for a simulation
with a long enough time elapsed. This characteristic implies that
simulating the behavior of a single site over a long enough simulation
time gives time-averaged representations of macroscopic observables like
coverages and <em>B</em> formation rates, which can be compared with those
quantities obtained from the mean field kinetic models derived above.
These time-averaged quantities are calculated next from a kMC
simulation.</p>

<p><em>Adapting the kMC code to simulate steady-state behaviors:</em></p>

<p><em>(link to code:
<a href="https://github.com/ari-fischer/kinetics_tutorial/tree/92e92c102a27a431a2ba9d655732d157fef8f4dc/KMC_tutorials">https://github.com/ari-fischer/kinetics_tutorial/tree/92e92c102a27a431a2ba9d655732d157fef8f4dc/KMC_tutorials</a>)</em></p>

<p>The model developed in the previous guide (to simulate thermodynamic
behaviors) includes a bath of reactant <em>A</em> and product <em>B</em>, initialized
at zero time as follows:</p>

<blockquote>

  <p>#initialize:</p>

  <p>N_A = 1000</p>

  <p>N_B = 0</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The catalyst surface interacts with the reservoir in each step of the
kMC simulation by either (i) removing <em>A</em> or <em>B</em> from the reservoir if
an adsorption event took place, or (ii) adding A or B to the reservoir
if the desorption of <em>A</em>* or <em>B</em>*, respectively, took place. For
instance, if the current state was a vacant site, and the selected move
for that step was to adsorb <em>A</em>, then one <em>A</em> was removed from the
reservoir (“N_A += -1”) and the state of the site was changed to the
<em>A</em>-covered state (“L = 1”), implemented as follows:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>for i in range(trials): #vacant site</p>

  <p>…</p>

  <p>if L == 0: #vacant site</p>

  <p>…</p>

  <p>if ind_move == 0: # A adsorption selected</p>

  <p>L = 1 # change from vacant site to A-covered site (A*)</p>

  <p>N_A += -1 # remove one species A from the reservoir</p>
</blockquote>

<p>As the simulation progresses, <em>A</em> is progressively consumed and <em>B</em>
generated until the ratio of <em>A</em> to <em>B</em> in the reservoir establishes
thermodynamic equilibrium. Such equilibration occurs because the
probabilities that <em>A</em> and <em>B</em> adsorb to a vacant site are proportional
to their mole fractions in the reservoir. Consequently, as <em>A</em> is
depleted, <em>A</em>* formation from <em>A</em> adsorption becomes slower, while an
increase in <em>B</em> increases the rate of <em>B</em>* formation from <em>B</em>
adsorption.</p>

<p>Steady-state kinetics for <em>A</em> conversion to <em>B</em> are instead obtained by
fixing the mole fractions of <em>A</em> and <em>B</em> in the reservoir so that the
probabilities for <em>A</em> and <em>B</em> adsorption do not change with the
simulation time. This is achieved by simply commenting out the “N_A +=
-1” line from the previous simulation so that the <em>A</em>-adsorption step
does not affect the amount of <em>A</em> in the reservoir. The same is done for
the <em>B</em>-desorption step (“N_B += 1”). We still, however, want to keep
track of the number of products formed during a simulation, so the we
define a number of products formed “N_P” initialized as:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>N_P = 0</p>

  <p>…</p>

  <p>N_Ps = list([N_P])</p>
</blockquote>

<p>And we add 1 to this every time <em>B</em> desorbs from the site:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>for i in range(trials): #vacant site</p>

  <p>…</p>

  <p>elif L == 2: #vacant site</p>

  <p>…</p>

  <p>if ind_move == 0: # A adsorption selected</p>

  <p>L = 0</p>

  <p>N_P += 1#add this one in as a tracer of products formed</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This N_P is simply a tracker of the number of <em>B</em> products formed, but
does not influence the frequencies of any steps (because no rate
constants depend on a <em>P</em> mole fraction).</p>

<p>Figure 2 shows the number of <em>B</em> products formed (from N_Ps) as a
function of simulation time for a simulation of 100,000 trial steps. The
number of products increase linearly with time reflecting steady-state
behavior. The rate of <em>P</em> product (per site) is given by the slope of
this trend.</p>

<p>Figure 2 also shows the trend on a shorter time interval (1000 steps).
The number of products formed is always an integer value, and jumps from
value to value after a varying amount of time elapses. The period
between increases in products formed reflects the time elapsed while
other moves that do not involve product formation occur (<em>A</em>*
adsorption, for instance), and the waiting time for <em>B</em>* to desorb. It
becomes clear on short time scales that the kMC simulation does not
report the number of products formed as continuous function (despite the
appearance of such over long timescales in Figure 2a), but is instead
discrete (because only integer numbers of product can form, not
fractions of one).</p>

<p><img src="/site/assets/images/KMC_tutorial_2/figure2.png" alt="figure 2" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 2:</strong> Number of products formed as a function of simulation time
after a long time (left) and shorter time interval (right).</p>

<p>Steady-state <em>B</em> formation rates and surface coverages are obtained by
taking time-averages of these quantities over a long enough simulation
time. Rates are obtained by normalizing the number of products formed by
the time elapsed:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>#calculate rates</p>

  <p>rates = np.sum(N_Ps)/np.sum(ts)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Coverages are obtained by finding the amount of time the system exists
in each state, and normalizing by the total simulation time, shown for a
vacant surface, for instance, with L=0:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>#convert Ls into np array, and get rid of last element to report time elapsed for coverages</p>

  <p>Ls_np = np.array(Ls[0:-1])</p>

  <p>#indexes where surface is vacant (L==0)</p>

  <p>L0_ind = np.where(Ls_np == 0)</p>

  <p>ts_np = np.array(ts)</p>

  <p>#time elapsed in for each instance where L==0</p>

  <p>time_L0 = np.sum(ts_np[L0_ind[0]+1]-ts_np[L0_ind[0]])</p>

  <p>#normalize vacant time with total elapsed time</p>

  <p>cov_v = time_L0/ts_np[-1]</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The simulation coverages and rates can be reported from these averages
as follows:</p>

<p>* coverage: 0.09190093419008047</p>

<p>A coverage: 0.9072329666594803</p>

<p>B coverage: 0.09190093419008047</p>

<p>rates: 0.0891111360522377</p>

<p><em>Comparing kMC simulation results to the mean-field kinetic
description:</em></p>

<p>The rate of <em>B</em> formation for a <em>y<sub>A</sub></em> value of unity was found to be
0.089 from the kMC simulation, which is similar to the pseudo-steady
state value obtained from the mean-field equation in equation 8 (0.091).
The trends for coverage and rates with changing <em>y<sub>A</sub></em> values, but
constant (zero) <em>y<sub>B</sub></em> values, are obtained by initializing the simulation
with different numbers of N_A, for a fixed total number of species in
the reservoir, denoted as N_tot:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p># initialize:</p>

  <p>…</p>

  <p>N_tot = 1000</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Then, kA_a and kB_a values are parameterized based on N_A and N_B
normalized by N_tot, instead of by the sum of N_A and N_B, to reflect
other inert species (like He) making up the balance in the reservoir:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>for i in range(trials):</p>

  <p>…</p>

  <p>if L == 0: #vacant site</p>

  <p>kA_a = kA_a0 * (N_A)/(N_tot)</p>

  <p>kB_a = kB_a0 * (N_B)/(N_tot)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Running the simulation for a series of N_A values, and constant N_tot
and N_B (zero), reproduces the trend from Figure 1. These data are shown
alongside the results from the mean field kinetic model in Figure 3. The
close agreement between mean-field descriptions and kMC simulations
shows how time-averaged behaviours from a reactions on single site with
discrete descriptions of site occupancy and product formation report the
same kinetic trends as continuous mean field descriptions. Such
agreement reflects the fact that the kMC simulation samples the same
distribution of states as the ensemble considered in deriving the
Langmuir-Hinshellwood kinetic expressions.</p>

<p><img src="/site/assets/images/KMC_tutorial_2/figure3.png" alt="figure 3" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 3:</strong> Coverage of <em>A</em>* and vacant *-sites (Left) and <em>B</em>
formation rates as a function of <em>y<sub>A</sub></em> mole fractions from mean-field
descriptions (MF) and time-averaged behaviours from kMC simulations
(kMC).</p>

<p><em>Exercises:</em></p>

<p>1. Compare rates obtained from different simulation times to see how
much the average values vary, and how long a sampling time is necessary
to obtain reliable reported values.</p>

<p>2. What changes to the rate constants in Table 1 invalidate the
assumptions made in deriving equation 8? How can this be probed with the
kMC simulation?</p>

<p>3. Adapt the code to consider a more complex reaction like
A&lt;-&gt;A*&lt;-&gt;B*&lt;-&gt;C*</p>

<p><em>References:</em></p>

<p>[1] Andersen M, Panosetti C, Reuter K. A Practical Guide to Surface
Kinetic Monte Carlo Simulations. Front Chem. 2019;7:202.</p>

<p>[2] Reaction rate theory and rare events (Chapter 14). B Peters.
Elsevier, 2017. ISBN: 978-0-444-56349-1</p>

<p><em>Appendix:</em></p>

<p>The sample code is available as a Jupyter notebook entitled
“kMC_A_B_rxn_single_site_eq.ipynb” at the ari-fischer GitHub page
(<a href="https://github.com/ari-fischer/">https://github.com/ari-fischer/</a>) in the “kinetics_tutorial”
repository under the “KMC_tutorials” folder</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Kinetics" /><category term="tutorials" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Run a simple kinetic Monte Carlo simulation for catalytic reaction kinetics in Python</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/site/kinetics/tutorials/2023/07/23/KMC_tutorial_1_equilibrium.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Run a simple kinetic Monte Carlo simulation for catalytic reaction kinetics in Python" /><published>2023-07-23T20:37:06+08:00</published><updated>2023-07-23T20:37:06+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/site/kinetics/tutorials/2023/07/23/KMC_tutorial_1_equilibrium</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/site/kinetics/tutorials/2023/07/23/KMC_tutorial_1_equilibrium.html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Introduction:</em></p>

<p>Kinetic Monte Carlo (kMC) is a powerful tool for studying reaction
kinetics when the set of important steps becomes too complicated for
exact analysis of deterministic rate equations. kMC is used to generate
stochastic trajectories through the space of possible metastable states
that the system can adopt. Important information about reaction dynamics
can be extracted from these trajectories, such as reaction rates and
rate constants. As a first step to running kMC simulations, a simple kMC code is developed to simulate a catalytic reaction as it proceeds towards thermodynamic equilibrium. The equilibrium behavior is shown to be consistent with that determined from the kinetic parameters. The next parts in the series will show how reaction rates are obtained from these simulations.</p>

<p><em>Tutorial:</em></p>

<p>(link to code: https://github.com/ari-fischer/kinetics_tutorial/tree/9e7ea49ca8f6c48bcc8ef1c22e1c0fb8d78b9a61/KMC_tutorials)</p>

<p>A simple catalytic reaction network for the conversion of species <em>A</em> to
<em>B</em> is depicted in Scheme 1. It consists of <em>A</em> adsorption at a
catalytic site (denoted by *) to form <em>A*</em> (step 1), <em>A*</em> conversion
to <em>B*</em> (step 2), and <em>B*</em> desorption to form <em>B.</em> Acid-catalyzed
1-butene isomerization to 2-butene (Scheme 2) is one example of a
reaction that follows these steps.</p>

<p><strong>Scheme 1</strong>: A sequence of elementary steps for the conversion of
species <em>A</em> to <em>B</em> on a catalytic site (denoted by *). The <em>k<sub>i</sub></em> terms
represent forward and reverse rate constants for each reaction step.</p>

<p><img src="/site/assets/images/KMC_tutorial_1/Scheme1.png" alt="Scheme1" /></p>

<p><strong>Scheme 2</strong>: A sequence of elementary steps for acid-catalyzed
1-butene isomerization to 2-butene.</p>

<p><img src="/site/assets/images/KMC_tutorial_1/Scheme2.png" alt="Scheme 2" /></p>

<p>Scheme 1 considers a catalytic site (*) that can be either (i) empty,
(ii) <em>A</em>-covered, or (iii) <em>B</em>-covered. Each state can transition into
others with frequencies represented by the rate constant for the
elementary reactions (Scheme 1). Table 1 shows the set of possible
initial states and the final states that are formed after a transition
along with the frequencies of these transitions.</p>

<p><img src="/site/assets/images/KMC_tutorial_1/Table1.png" alt="Table 1" /></p>

<p>The procedure required to execute a transition from a given initial
state is shown next as an illustrative example. The reader is referred
to publications by Peters [1] and Andersen et al. [2] for more
details regarding the algorithm and its implementation. The procedure
for transition from an initial state, <em>i</em>, is outlined in the following:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Identify all possible transitions from initial <em>i</em> state and their
corresponding frequencies.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Compute the net rate of transition from state <em>i</em> (denoted by
<em>k<sub>i,tot</sub></em>) from the sum over the frequencies of each possible
transition to the new state <em>j</em> (<em>k<sub>i,tot</sub></em> = ∑<sub>j</sub> <em>k<sub>i,j</sub></em>).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Select a random number (<em>u<sub>1</sub></em>) between 0 and 1.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Find the value of <em>j</em> that satisfies the following relation to
determine which transition occurs:</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p><em>k<sub>i,j-1</sub></em> / <em>k<sub>i,tot</sub></em> &lt; <em>u<sub>1</sub></em> &lt; <em>k<sub>i,j</sub></em> / <em>k<sub>i,tot</sub></em></p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Replace state <em>i</em> with the selected state <em>j</em>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Select another random number (<em>u<sub>2</sub></em>) between 0 and 1.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Update the simulation time (<em>t</em>) by adding the waiting time (Δ<em>t</em>)
computed by sampling the probability density for the first
transition out of state <em>I</em> to occur (Δ<em>t</em> =-ln(<em>u<sub>2</sub></em>)/<em>k<sub>i,tot</sub></em>)
[1].</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Repeat steps 1-8.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>The steps outlined above are implemented in a Jupyter notebook (with
Python 3) to simulate the reaction dynamics. A sample code is available on Github (see appendix for details).</p>

<p>First, numpy, scipy, and pyplot modules are imported:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>import numpy as np</p>

  <p>import scipy as sci</p>

  <p>import matplotlib.pyplot as plt</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Next, the values of the rate constants in Scheme 1 are specified (Table
2).</p>

<p><img src="/site/assets/images/KMC_tutorial_1/Table2.png" alt="Table 2" /></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>kA_a0 = 10 # A adsorption constant</p>

  <p>kB_a0 = 1 # B adsorption constant</p>

  <p>kA_d = 1 # A desorption constant</p>

  <p>k_AB = .1 # A conversion to B</p>

  <p>kB_d = .1 # B desorption constant</p>

  <p>k_BA = .01 # B conversion to A</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The state of the system is then initialized. At time zero, the
surface is uncovered. This is denoted by an index of 0. Indexes of 1 and
2 represent A- and B-covered surfaces, respectively. The active site is exposed to a bath initially
containing 1000 molecules of <em>A</em> and zero molecules of <em>B</em>. The simulation with proceed for 100000 events:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p># initial parameters #</p>

  <p>t = 0 # initial time</p>

  <p>L = 0 # initial state: 0 – empty; 1 – A*; 2 – B*</p>

  <p>N_A = 1000 # number of A</p>

  <p>N_B = 0 # number of B</p>

  <p>trials = 100000</p>

  <p># vector for A, B, and t #</p>

  <p>N_As = list([N_A])</p>

  <p>N_Bs = list([N_B])</p>

  <p>ts = list([t])</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The trajectory is now ready to be simulated with the parameterized rate
constants and initial state specified. The specified number of trials are executed by
implementation in a for loop. Each execution of the loop performs
steps 1-7, then repeats the same code using the final state from the previous execution. The following code uses an intuitive (albeit inefficient)
implementation with nested if statements used for purposes of
illustration. To start, the loop is entered and two random numbers are
drawn:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>for i in range(trials):</p>

  <p>u1 = np.random.rand(1) #rand for the particular process selected</p>

  <p>u2 = np.random.rand(1) #rand for the time step</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Next, an if statement is used to determine which process to execute
depending on the initial state:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>if L == 0: #vacant site</p>

  <p>…</p>

  <p>elif L == 1: # A covered</p>

  <p>…</p>

  <p>elif L == 2: #B covered</p>

  <p>…</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Then, the rate constants for transition from the current state are
determined and constructed into an array (with an initial state of 0 as
an example). The rate constant for <em>A</em> and <em>B</em> adsorption are multiplied
by the molar fractions of A and B, respectively, to get rates:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>if L == 0: #vacant site</p>

  <p>#adsorption</p>

  <p>kA_a = kA_a0 * (N_A)/(N_A + N_B) #adsorption rate of A based on
prevalent A mole fraction</p>

  <p>kB_a = kB_a0 * (N_B)/(N_A + N_B) #adsorption rate of B based on
prevalent B mole fraction</p>

  <p>ks = np.array([kA_a,kB_a])</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Then, the move to take is selected by comparing <em>u~1~</em> to a cumulative
array of the ks of possible events.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>k_tot = np.sum(ks) # get the total rate of transition from the sum of
ks</p>

  <p>k_stack = np.cumsum(ks) # get a cumulative array of ks for event
selection</p>

  <p>select = n1*k_tot # find the value in the cumulative array to select</p>

  <p>#pick the first one that is larger than the select criteria</p>

  <p>indexes = np.arange(len(k_stack))</p>

  <p>ind_move = indexes[k_stack&gt;select][0]</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Next, the state of the system is updated depending on the move selected.
If the move is 0, meaning <em>A</em> adsorbs, the next state becomes 1 (<em>A*</em>)
and one <em>A</em> molecule is removed from the gas phase.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>if ind_move == 0:</p>

  <p>L = 1</p>

  <p>N_A += -1</p>

  <p>elif ind_move == 1:</p>

  <p>L = 2</p>

  <p>N_B += -1</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The rate constants for transition from the initial state are obtained
and the next move is executed using a similar procedure to that outlined
above when L= 1 or 2. The waiting time is then evaluated outside of the
if statement using the frequency for transition computed and updates the
simulation time:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>t += - np.log(n2)/k_tot #t estable</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Finally, the new times and numbers of <em>A</em> and <em>B</em> are appended to their
respective vectors to tract their time evolutions:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>ts.append(t[0])</p>

  <p>N_As.append(N_A)</p>

  <p>N_Bs.append(N_B)…</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The system is evolved using the code above for 100000 steps. The first
few states for a single trajectory are printed with corresponding time
intervals as follows:</p>

<p>Ls = (0,1,0,1,2,0,1,0,1, …)</p>

<p>ts = (0.26, 0.48, 0.15, 0.21, 0.05, 0.33, 1.7, …)</p>

<p>The mole fractions of <em>A</em> (<em>y<sub>A</sub></em>) and <em>B</em> (<em>y<sub>B</sub></em>) species present in
the gas phase are plotted as a function of the simulation time (Figure
1). Recall that the number of <em>A</em> or <em>B</em> decreases by one unit every
time the state transitions from 0 to 1 or 2, respectively. Their values
increase by one unit every time the state transitions from either 1 or 2
to 0, respectively. The fraction of <em>A</em> decreases asymptotically towards
an equilibrium value of around 0.11 while <em>B</em> increases asymptotically
towards an equilibrium value of around 0.89. Their values approach this
stable equilibrium value as fractions of <em>A</em> and <em>B</em> adjust to establish
detailed balance.</p>

<p><img src="/site/assets/images/KMC_tutorial_1/Figure1.png" alt="Figure 1" /></p>

<p>The fraction of <em>B</em> (divided by <em>A</em> corresponds to an equilibrium
constant (<em>K<sub>AB</sub></em>) of 9.9 via through <em>K<sub>AB</sub></em> = <em>y<sub>B</sub></em> / <em>y<sub>A</sub></em>. The
equilibrium behavior is compared to the value obtained from
deterministic equations derived from the elementary steps in Scheme 1. A
relation between reactants and products for each elementary step in
quasi-equilibrium is obtained as follows:</p>

<p><img src="/site/assets/images/KMC_tutorial_1/Eq1.png" alt="Eq 1" /></p>

<p>Here, the θ terms denote fractional surface coverages of A, B, or empty (*) sites. Solving this set of algebraic equations for the <em>y<sub>B</sub></em> / <em>y<sub>A</sub></em> ratio
gives a definition of <em>K<sub>AB</sub></em> in terms of the forward and reverse rate
constants in Scheme 1:</p>

<p><img src="/site/assets/images/KMC_tutorial_1/Eq2.png" alt="Eq 2" /></p>

<p>The <em>K<sub>AB</sub></em> determined from these rate constants is 10.0, in close
agreement with the value obtained from the stable behavior in the
trajectory.</p>

<p><em>Exercises:</em></p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>How do changes to the rate constants affect the equilibrium ratio?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>How do changes to the rate constants affect the time it takes to
reach a stable <em>A-B</em> ratio?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>How can the code be modified to obtain steady-state reaction rates
for A conversion to B at a fixed A mole fraction (<em>y<sub>A</sub></em>)?</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p><em>The next post in the series will show a solution to exercise 3</em></p>

<p><em>References:</em></p>

<p>[1] Reaction rate theory and rare events. B Peters. Elsevier, 2017. ISBN: 978-0-444-56349-1</p>

<p>[2] Andersen M, Panosetti C, Reuter K. A Practical Guide to Surface Kinetic Monte Carlo Simulations. Front Chem. 2019;7:202.</p>

<p><em>Appendix:</em></p>

<p>The sample code is available as a Jupyter notebook entitled
“kMC_A_B_rxn_single_site_eq.ipynb” at the ari-fischer GitHub page
(<a href="https://github.com/ari-fischer/">https://github.com/ari-fischer/</a>) in the “kinetics_tutorial”
repository under the “KMC_tutorials” folder</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Kinetics" /><category term="tutorials" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Introduction:]]></summary></entry></feed>